Finding Aid for James Leach Photonegatives, 1938-1958
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James Leach Photonegatives 1938-1958, 1943-1957
Leach, James.
227 folders (in 3 boxes)
0661 Aa/2
Ann Arbor, Michigan photographer. Photonegatives of Ann Arbor area businesses, service and fraternal organizations, school and other youth groups.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The negatives were donated by James and Janice Leach (donor no. 9709 ) in March 2006.
The collection is open to research.
James Leach worked as a professional photographer in Ann Arbor throughout the 1930s, 40s and 50s. Over the course of this career, he saved a number of negatives of Southeastern Michigan local businesses, organizations, and prominent individuals. While the bulk of Leach's work was made up of private studio portraiture, a number of the photos document the region's commercial architecture, advertisements, and social culture of the period.
The James Leach photographic collection consists entirely of celluloid negatives in three boxes. The first two boxes are composed of 4X5" prints, while the third is an oversize box containing the 5X7" negatives as noted in the contents list. The bulk of these materials are images depicting Ann Arbor business and educational institutions as well as athletic and community organizations. There is also a select number of Detroit-area photographs, as labeled. These materials are divided into four main series: Business and Commerce, Youth Activities and Educational Facilities, Community Organizations, Groups and Institutions, and Miscellaneous Photographs.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor Home and School for Handicapped Children.; Ann Arbor High School (Mich.); Construction--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Drugstores--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Grocery stores--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Industrial facilities--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Fraternal organizations--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Masonic organizations--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Salvation Army--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Slauson Junior High School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Masonic Temple (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Zal-Gaz Grotto (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Appliance stores--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Window displays--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Restaurants--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Stores and shops--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Taxicabs--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Business and commerce
  Business and Commerce, the first series, contains a number of both interior and exterior images of area businesses, and is divided into eight sub-series: Restaurants, Grocery and Drug Stores, Shoes and Apparel, Automotive Related, Industry, Construction and Demolition, Appliances and Electronics, and Other. Of particular interest are the differing types of period commercial architecture and interior design, as well as the large amount of window and shop advertisement displays featured throughout the various types of retail sub-series.
  - Restaurants
    - Curtis Restaurant (Box 1)
      (interior)
    - Fritz Metzger's Restaurant (Box 1)
    - Leo Ping (Box 1)
    - Temple Dining (Box 1)
    - Thompson's Dairy Bar (Box 1)
      (interior and exterior)
    - Old German Restaurant (Box 1)
      (exterior and group of U.S. Marines)
    - Unidentified Restaurant (Box 1)
      (exterior photos of Coca-Cola sign)
  - Grocery and Drug Stores
    - 8th Street Grocery (Box 1)
      (interior photos of hygiene product display)
    - B.E. Muehlig Dry Goods (Box 1)
      (exterior)
    - Dulgeroff Market June 30, 1943 (Box 1)
    - Dulgeroff Market (Box 1)
    - Jefferson Street Grocery (Box 1)
    - Packard Kroger Store (Box 1)
      (interior photo of turkey display)
    - Peck Drug (Box 1)
      (interior photo of hair curler display)
    - Unidentified Drug Store (Box 1)
      (interior photo of man and tobacco display)
  - Shoes and Apparel
    - Deese Furs August 2, 1952 (Box 1)
    - Deese Furs (Box 1)
      (interior photo of hanging fur coats)
    - Deese Furs (Box 1)
      (color, interior)
    - Deese Furs (Box 1)
      (photos of fur-making process)
    - Fiegel's (Box 1)
      (exterior and window display)
    - Fiegel's (Box 1)
      (sign and men's clothing window display)
    - Kline's Department Store (Box 1)
      (women's clothing window display with mannequins)
    - Kline's Department Store (Box 1)
      (men's clothing window display)
    - Kresge's April 29, 1943 (Box 1)
      (interior photos of men's clothing counters)
    - Rabideau and Harris Clothiers November, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Rabideau and Harris Clothiers (Box 1)
    - Stein and Goetz Sporting Goods (Box 1)
      (exterior and window displays)
    - Wagner's (Box 1)
      (window display)
    - Wagner's (Box 1)
      (interior photo of counter display)
    - Wanty and Reule October, 1952 (Box 1)
      (athletic shoe window display)
    - Wanty and Reule 1952 (Box 1)
    - Wanty and Reule (Box 1)
  - Automotive Related
    - The Automobile Equipment Company (Box 1)
    - Fram Filter Corporation (Box 1)
    - Fram Filter Corporation (Box 1)
      (exterior photos of "dust tunnel" building)
      (see 5x7 negatives in box 3)
    - Link Motors, Ypsilanti Exhibit (Box 1)
      (Studebaker display)
    - Mac's Auto Mart (Box 1)
      (used car lot)
    - Manausa Car Wash (Box 1)
      (interior and workers)
    - Manausa Service Station 1126 South University (Box 1)
    - Radio Cab Company (Box 1)
      (exterior and individual cabs)
    - Radio Cab Company (Box 1)
      (individual cabs)
    - Western Auto (Box 1)
    - Western Auto (Box 1)
      (interior and exterior photos of multiple store locations)
    - Whizzer Bike Exhibit (Box 1)
      (motorbike display)
    - Unlabeled Taxi Photos (Box 1)
      (various local taxi company cab signs)
  - Industry
    - American Broach and Machine Company (Box 1)
      (machinery and workers)
    - Ann Arbor Foundry (Box 1)
      (various manhole and drain covers)
    - Ann Arbor Press (Box 1)
      (printing equipment and workers)
    - Eberbach and Son Company (Box 1)
      (workers and offices)
    - Michigan Consolidated Gas Company (Box 1)
    - Precision Parts (Box 1)
    - Woods Manufacturing Company (Box 1)
    - Unlabeled Factory, "Economy Baler T-1" (Box 1)
  - Construction and Demolition
    - Bryant and Detwiler Company (Box 1)
      (birds-eye and ground level photos of construction)
    - Davis Construction September 7, 1950 (Box 1)
      (construction)
    - Davis Construction November 6, 1950 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Bell Telephone Company (Box 1)
    - Michigan Bell Telephone Company (Box 1)
      (workers laying cable)
    - Montgomery Ward (Box 1)
    - Shartzer Wrecking Company August 14-15 (Box 1)
      (demolition)
    - Shartzer Wrecking Company (Box 1)
    - Visel Trucking Company (Box 1)
      (excavation and equipment)
    - Zion Lutheran Church (Box 1)
    - Unlabeled swimming pool (Box 1)
  - Appliances and Electronics
    - Gas Company (Box 1)
      (woman with appliances)
    - H.C. Scheve and H. Max Koch (Box 1)
      (burner display)
    - Johnson and Company General Electric Store (Box 1)
      (appliance salesman and customers)
    - Johnson and Company General Electric Store (Box 1)
    - Johnson and Company General Electric Store (Box 1)
      (interior and window displays)
    - Johnson and Company General Electric Store (Box 1)
    - Michigan Bell Telephone Company (Box 1)
      (appliance display)
    - Modern Appliance (Box 1)
    - Unlabeled Detroit Furniture Store (Box 1)
      (appliance window display)
  - Other
    - Ann Arbor Bank (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor News (Box 1)
    - April Insurance (Box 1)
    - Klager Hatchery (Box 1)
      (various interior and exterior)
    - Marilyn Inn (Box 1)
    - National Bank Building (Box 1)
      (exterior showing entire building, including Hogan Hayes Furs)
    - Paul Nolting Florist (Box 1)
    - State Theatre (Box 1)
- Youth Activities and Educational Facilities
  The Youth Activities and Educational Facilities series is made up of a miscellaneous category and three additional sub-series, each depicting a different type of Ann Arbor youth institution. The first sub-series shows images from the Dr. Arnold Kambly Ann Arbor Home and School for Handicapped Children. Included among these images are large numbers of photos of the building's exterior and grounds, as well as interior images of the facilities and photos of the students. The next sub-series is composed entirely of athletic team portraits, primarily boys' football, from Herbert M Slauson Junior High School. Following this is an assortment of group portraiture of various clubs and athletic teams, as well as a selection of snapshots, from The Omega--the Ann Arbor High School Yearbook--taken in the late 1940s and early 1950s.
  - Dr. Arnold Kambly and the Ann Arbor Home and School for Handicapped Children
    - January 10, 1942 (Box 1)
      (interior of bedrooms and classrooms)
    - September 15, 1942 (Box 1)
      (exterior of building and grounds)
    - October 10, 1943 (Box 1)
    - 1946 (Box 1)
    - February, 1955 (Box 1)
      (interior, various)
    - Undated (Box 1)
      (exterior and interior)
    - Undated (Box 1)
      (children in various outdoor and indoor activities)
  - Herbert M. Slauson Junior High School
    - 1948 (Box 1)
      (football team portraits)
    - 1950 (Box 1)
    - 1951 (Box 1)
    - 1953 (Box 1)
    - 1954 (Box 1)
    - March 15, 1954 (Box 1)
      (boys and girls basketball team portraits)
    - 1955 (Box 1)
      (yearbook portraits of various boys and girls sports teams)
  - Ann Arbor High School
    - 1947 (Box 1)
      (portraits of various boys and girls clubs and sports teams)
    - Unlabeled 1948 (Box 1)
      (portraits of various girls clubs and sports teams)
    - Omega 1949 (Box 1)
      (yearbook portraits of various boys and girls clubs and sports teams)
    - Omega 1949 (Box 1)
    - Omega 1951 (Box 1)
    - Unlabeled 1952 (Box 1)
    - Unlabeled 1953 (Box 1)
    - Omega 1954 (Box 2)
    - Omega 1954 (Box 2)
    - Omega, "Winning Teams," Undated (Box 2)
    - "Individuals and Groups," Undated (Box 2)
      (various students at work)
    - "Ftb -- Cook," (Box 2)
    - "Sophomore," Undated (Box 2)
      (sophomore football team portraits)
    - "Sophomore," Undated (Box 2)
      (sophomore football team portrait)
    - "Cross Country," Undated (Box 2)
      (cross country team portraits)
    - "Library," Undated (Box 2)
      (school library with working students)
  - Other
    - Ann Arbor Bulldogs 1947 (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor Bulldogs 1948 (Box 2)
    - Beckman School (Box 2)
      (girls swim team)
    - Jones School (Box 2)
    - KC (Box 2)
      (Knights of Columbus?)
      (boys basketball team portraits)
    - Tappan School (Box 2)
      (home economics classroom)
    - Whitmore Lake School (Box 2)
    - Unlabeled Football Team 1951 (Box 2)
      (action shots of team)
- Community Organizations, Groups and Institutions
  The Community Organizations, Groups and Institutions series contains eight sub-series featuring images showing a wide variety of Ann Arbor and Washtenaw Country groups posing for portraits and attending organization-related activities. The sub-series are broken down based on the specific group, or type of group. They are: American Legion, Kiwanis, Salvation Army, Disabled American Veterans, Boys and Girl Scouts, Zion Evangelical Church Choir, Jim Servis Orchestra, and Fraternal Organizations. This last sub-series is divided into three sub-sub-series, which show several different area Masonic chapters, Shriners, and Elks. The last sub-series is a collection of organizations unrelated to any other category.
  - American Legion
    - American Legion 1951 (Box 2)
      (new year's celebration)
    - American Legion 1953 (Box 2)
      (parade float construction)
    - American Legion (Box 2)
      (various group portraits)
  - Kiwanis
    - Kiwanis Club, Ann Arbor, Michigan October 9, 1942 (Box 2)
      (war bond window display)
    - Kiwanis Club, Chelsea, Michigan (Box 2)
      (various groups in clown costumes)
  - Salvation Army
    - Salvation Army February 26, 1952 (Box 2)
      (organization members and band)
    - Salvation Army 1953 (Box 2)
      (Christmas doll collection)
    - Salvation Army 1954 (Box 2)
      (United Youth Group portrait)
    - Salvation Army 1955 (Box 2)
      (Salvation Army Scouts group portrait)
    - Salvation Army May 22, 1956 (Box 2)
      (banquet)
    - Salvation Army 1957 (Box 2)
    - Salvation Army (Box 2)
    - Salvation Army (Box 2)
      (anniversary celebration)
    - Salvation Army (Box 2)
    - Salvation Army (Box 2)
      (group snapshot)
    - Salvation Army (Box 2)
  - Disabled American Veterans
    - Disabled American Veterans 1956 (Box 2)
      (officers)
    - Disabled American Veterans 1956 (Box 2)
      (various group snapshots)
    - Disabled American Veterans (Box 2)
    - Disabled American Veterans (Box 2)
      (television set display)
  - Boy and Girl Scouts
    - Girl Scouts (Box 2)
      (group portraits)
    - Girl Scouts (Box 2)
      (varying group portraits)
    - Girl Scouts (Box 2)
    - Boy Scouts (Box 2)
      (varying group portraits and project displays)
  - Zion Evangelical Lutheran Church Choir
    - Choir 1955 (Box 2)
      (portrait)
    - Choir 1957 (Box 2)
  - Jim Servis Orchestra
    - Orchestra December 31, 1952 (Box 2)
      (Ypsilanti Armory performance)
    - Orchestra May, 1956 (Box 2)
      (performance)
    - Orchestra January, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Fraternal Organizations
    - Masons
      - Masonic Temple (Box 2)
      - Masonic Temple (Box 2)
        (renovated exterior)
      - Ann Arbor Council 1950 (Box 2)
      - Ann Arbor Council 1956-1957 (Box 2)
      - Ann Arbor Council, R&S Masters 1957 (Box 2)
        (installation)
      - Ann Arbor Council, R&S Masters (Box 2)
      - Ann Arbor Lodge 1945 (Box 2)
      - Ann Arbor Lodge 1957 (Box 2)
      - Ann Arbor Lodge (Box 2)
      - Commandery June 6, 1943 (Box 2)
        (ascension)
      - Commandery 1944 (Box 2)
      - Commandery, "Mortons" (Box 2)
      - Council -- Super Ex (Box 2)
        (members in full uniform)
      - De Molay December, 1943 (Box 2)
      - De Molay 1957 (Box 2)
      - Fraternity Lodge 1952 (Box 2)
      - Fraternity Lodge 1954-1955 (Box 2)
      - Golden Rule 1938 (Box 2)
      - Golden Rule 1939 (Box 2)
      - Golden Rule 1941 (Box 2)
      - Golden Rule 1942 (Box 2)
      - Golden Rule 1946, 1947, 1948 (Box 2)
      - Golden Rule November 12, 1951 (Box 2)
      - Golden Rule 1952 (Box 2)
      - Golden Rule 1953 (Box 2)
      - Golden Rule 1954 (Box 2)
      - Golden Rule 1955 (Box 2)
      - Golden Rule 1956 (Box 2)
      - Golden Rule 1957 (Box 2)
      - Golden Rule 1958 (Box 2)
      - Golden Rule (Box 2)
      - Order of the Eastern Star 1944-1945 (Box 2)
      - Order of the Eastern Star 1956 (Box 2)
      - Order of the Eastern Star (Box 2)
      - Royal Arch 1943 (Box 2)
      - Royal Arch (Box 2)
      - Washtenaw Chapter 1944 (Box 2)
      - Washtenaw Chapter, 1956-1957 (Box 2)
      - Washtenaw Chapter 1957 (Box 2)
      - Zal-Gaz Grotto July 17, 1943 (Box 2)
        ("grotto calliope" truck advertising grotto and the purchasing of war bonds)
      - Zal-Gaz Grotto (Box 2)
        (charter members)
      - Zal-Gaz Grotto (Box 2)
        (portrait of Mr. William Cheatham, grotto member)
      - Zal-Gaz Grotto (Box 2)
        (portrait of Mr. Lyle Kett, grotto member)
      - Zal-Gaz Grotto (Box 2)
        (portrait of Mr. Walter Seylter, grotto member)
      - Zal-Gaz Grotto (Box 2)
        (portrait of Mrs. Lottie Trew, grotto member)
      - Zal-Gaz Grotto (Box 2)
        (portrait of Mr. John Young, grotto member, positive photograph included)
    - Shriners
      - Shriners 1953 (Box 2)
        (dinner photos at the American Legion)
      - White Shrine 1952 (Box 2)
      - White Shrine 1957 (Box 2)
      - White Shrine (Box 2)
    - Elks
      - Elks February 24, 1943 (Box 2)
        (initiation)
      - Elks February, 1944 (Box 2)
        (group portrait at Masonic Temple)
  - Other
    - Ann Arbor Optimist Club 1951 (Box 2)
      (birthday celebration)
    - Ann Arbor Optimist Club (Box 2)
      (solo and group member portraits)
    - Bowling Association (Box 2)
      (action shots and group portraits)
    - Eagles Baseball Team (Box 2)
      (group portrait with trophy)
    - Hereford Society (Box 2)
      (various shots of farmers and cattle)
    - Institute of Public Health (Box 2)
      (lab and researchers)
    - Michigan Bell Employees 1954 (Box 2)
      (woman's baseball team portrait)
    - Michigan Bell Employees (Box 2)
      (book drive)
    - University of Michigan Employees Union, Local 378 January 19, 1957 (Box 2)
    - Warren Quartet (Box 2)
      (members singing and portrait)
    - Ypsilanti Band June 6, 1943 (Box 2)
      (portrait outside Masonic Temple)
- Miscellaneous Photographs
  The Miscellaneous Photographs series contains a small sample of the wedding and funeral photographs commissioned over the course of Leach's career. Also included in this series is a small selection of Ann Arbor buildings and locations unrelated to the other series of the collection.
  - Weddings
    - Kidd Haeussler (Box 2)
    - Podenta (Box 2)
    - Schwab (Box 2)
    - Miss Ulmerf 1547 Washtenaw (Box 2)
  - Funerals
    - Basom (Box 2)
    - Hamlin Baby (Box 2)
    - Lunsford (Box 2)
    - MaCanallen (Box 2)
    - Mulfreed (Box 2)
    - Neil Baby (Box 2)
    - Skipper (Box 2)
      (color)
    - Uphaus Baby (Box 2)
  - Other
    - Ann Arbor Fire Department (Box 2)
      (exterior of fire house and Fire Prevention Week displays)
    - Burton Memorial Tower Carillon Bell, University of Michigan (Box 2)
    - Groomes Beach (Box 2)
    - Groomes Beach (Box 2)
  - 5x7 negatives (Box 3)
    (described above)
  - Photographer's project index (Box 3)